Finding Aid for Letters, Documents, & Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Letters, Documents, and Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
  - 1863 November 5. Newspaper; Detroit, Michigan, 4 pages; Detroit Advertiser and Tribune, vol. 28, no. 126. Page 2 features a letter to the Editor by Alpheus W. Tucker, an African American student asked to leave the University of Michigan on account of his race. Discusses the expulsion, reflects on the racial antagonism and "Copperheadism" at the University that motivated it, and opposition to the injustice. "... received a note from Prof. Ford, stating that there was quite an objection amongst the students to my attendance, and that the Faculty had blamed him for receiving my name, and he thought it best that, to prevent an outburst amongst the students, I had better leave." Located in Oversize Manuscripts. See also William Byrns ALS to Mrs. William Byrns, Ann Arbor, Michigan, November 11, 1863, for further discussion of the expulsion.
  - [18]63 November 25. M[ichael] Jacobs ALS to S[amuel] W. Crawford; Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, 2 pages; Respecting Jacobs's recent book, "Rebel Invasion" [Notes on the rebel invasion of Maryland and Pennsylvania, and the battle of Gettysburg, July 1st, 2d and 3d, 1863]. Crawford apparently liked the book and has some additional information for Jacobs about "these terrific struggles, in which you & your 'Pa. Reserves' took so distinguished a part." Edward Everett mentioned it during his recent speech, which has helped facilitate sales. The 10,000 copy edition will soon be sold and an enlarged edition will probably follow.
  - 1864 January 18. J[no.?] Milledge ALS to A[bner] J. Leavenworth; s.l., 2 pages; Dr. Stiles recently made a public appeal "to awaken our people to their danger." Asked Milledge to do likewise. Milledge seeks assistance with the writing of a lecture or address on the topic, "Our lives our fortunes and our most sacred honor." Hopes to increase Confederate patriotism. "It is the army in the rear and not in the front that we have to beat back and overcome."
  - 1864 January 29. E[rastus] D[ow] Palmer ALS to Frederic E[dwin] Church; Albany, [New York], 4 pages; Palmer requests Church to send him "Stewarts' picture" for an exhibition. He describes overworking himself in his studio, and mentions his sculptures "Peace Found," "Peri," "Evening," "Mercy Pleading" and compares his work on "Evening" to his previous sculpture, "Sappho." Notes a portrait of himself painted by Elliott.
  - 1864 April 13. Thomas Keith and Agnes Keith DS to Parlee Keith; Plymouth, [Massachusetts], 2 pages; Sale of half-part of a pew from the "Meeting House of the Union Society of East & West Bridgewater." Witnessed and signed by B. W. Keith, Justice of the Peace.
  - 1864 May 3. E[ben] N[orton] Horsford ALS to W[illia]m Cullen Bryant; Cambridge, [Massachusetts], 2 pages; Thanks for a favorable review in the Evening Post of Horsford's plan to use roasted wheat for Army rations. Notes how armies of the past, including the "troops besieging Carthage," did likewise.
  - 1864 September 13. Thomas Hill ALS to Augustus Story; Harvard College, [Cambridge, Massachusetts], 4 pages; Discusses Story's "proposed gift to Harvard College" and matters with donation handling. "One motive for founding a scholarship may not occur to you, --it would be a very pleasant thing to very many friends of the College to have the honorable & highly honored name of your family thus perpetuated on our books." Comments on the selection of scholarship recipients.
  - 1864 October 3. [Horatio G. Wright] ALS to Ed H. Wright; Harrisonburg, [Virginia], 4 pages; Affectionate letter to son describing his tent and a marvelous dog. "He is not a bit afraid in a fight and capers about without caring for the bullets... I call him Pete because I got him at Petersburg when he was a puppy." Have had two fights and chased enemy to Harrisonburg area. Written on Headquarters Sixth Army Corps stationery.
  - 1864 October 20. J[ames] G[illespie] Blaine ALS to Schuyler Colfax; Augusta, Maine, 4 pages; Urging Colfax to remain as Speaker of the House and not accept a Cabinet post.
  - 1864 December 18. D[avid] Wilmot ALS to Ulysses Mercur; Washington, [D.C.], 2 pages; Wilmot believes the election of Landon to the Senate would cause Republican party difficulties. He will try to get the President to offer him a judgeship instead; enlists Mercur's help in doing so.
  - 1864. 2 printed Docs.; Syracuse, [New York], 2 pages (total); "Syracuse School" Senior Class annual exams for History and Arithmetic.
  - 1865 March 14. W[illiam] W[inston] Seaton ALS to W[illia]m Gunton; Washington, [D.C.], 2 pages; William W. Seaton, editor of the National Intelligencer to William Gunton, President of the Bank of Washington. Regarding Seaton's claim against the estate of Joseph Gales and a postponement of debts owed to the Bank of Washington. Illinois Coal Stock and properties assigned to Mr. Carlisle will be used to settle debts to the Bank of Washington. A bond of [Robert] Olyphant, President of the "Delaware and Lacawanna [Lackawanna]" Railroad Company will serve as security.
  - 1865 April 9-10. E. B. Young ALS to Edward; Hudson, [New York], 6 pages; Admonishes Edward for not writing his family more frequently. Advises him not to marry "till you have means and an income sufficient to support both of you and can lay up something besides for a wet day, sick days & finally old age." Warns Edward against ruinous practices, including "tavern haunting, drinking, associating with bad women, gambling, and an inordinate patronizing of Livery Teams & stables all these keep a man poor in purse & character." Notes characteristics one should seek in a spouse, especially good education, practical economy, and housewifery skills. "...recollect that marriage is a lottery, both parties to it trying to entrap each other by hiding their bad qualities to come out bitterly after marriage." Warns Edward about marrying "a 1st full blooded cousin," noting potential birth defects and believing it criminal. "...I don't want you mortified for life or me to have fools for grandchildren." Believes the country will rebound after the end of the Civil War. Experiencing some difficulties due to the high price of silk. Mentions fabrics, clothing, and other items purchased for his mother, including a reference to false teeth: "...as soon as I get her new Teeth I think I shall have as good looking an old woman as any man has, and you need not be ashamed of her." Briefly notes a local celebration of [Robert E.] Lee's (1807-1870) surrender, "a General Illumination & Torch light procession &c."
  - 1865 April 13. George S. Boutwell ALS to Schuyler Colfax; Groton, Massachusetts, 3 pages; Praises Colfax's address on education. Notes the importance of education. Celebrates recent victories and the closing of the Civil War. This is a triumph such as mankind have never before witnessed,-- a triumph of the people not only over rebels and tyrants, but also over the unnatural and inhuman distinctions of society by which some enjoy the rights, privileges and property which justly belong to others."
  - [18]65 May 25. Will H. Githens ALS to Wife; Near Alexandria, Virginia, 4 pages; Letter from Regimental Surgeon, 78th Ill. Vol. Infantry regarding the recently completed Grand Review of the Army. He describes their welcome, the attendance and decorations, seeing Sherman and the President, and the monumental nature of the occasion. Contrasts the generosity of the women against Confederate women, who "would rather cut our throats than give us a mouthful of food." "...the world will never see the like again. I have no idea such immense armies will ever be called for in this or any other country again. I feel proud that I was one of them, and glad that I was permitted to see it - proud also that I am a Western soldier..."
  - 1865 May 31. James Speed ALS; Wash[ington, D.C.], 2 pages; Signed as Attorney General and written shortly after President Johnson issued a proclamation of general amnesty. To a former Confederate: "I am glad to learn your purpose to return to loyalty & duty. Permit me to say however that it pained me to see you writing about ‘my government' - This government is... as much yours as mine. The sooner this fact is felt & acknowledged the better. It seems to me that until such is your feeling, you cannot begin to be what I know you desire to be a good citizen."
  - 1865 August 18. Charles Lanman ALS to E[vert] A[ugustus] Duyckinck; Stratford, Connecticut, 2 pages; Expressing irritation at exclusion from Duyckinck's Cyclopaedia of American Literature. Threatens to make this mistreatment public and question his "conduct as a compiler." Lists some of his accolades and honors. Includes Duyckinck's reply dated at New York, 1865 August 21.
  - 1865 August 21. Evert Duyckinck ALS to Cha[rle]s Lanman; New York, [New York], 4 pages; Responding to Charles Lanman's indignant letter [dated August 18, 1865] about being excluded from the new edition of the Cyclopaedia of American Literature. Assures Lanman that his omission was not mean-spirited but due to the absence of a reply to a circular sent to him. Sending another circular and notes the information required. Found Lanman's letter unjust to himself and Mr. Scribner.
  - [ca. 1865?] [after 1830?]. AMs; s.l., 23 pages; Manuscript copy of portions of "Reminiscences of Philadelphia," by Sarah Hall (1761-1830) published in Selections of the Writings of Mrs. Sarah Hall (1833). Account of manners, customs, buildings, fashions, and the state of society in Philadelphia preceding the Revolution. Comments on servants and slaves. Includes a newspaper clipping from ca. February 7, 1822, about organized burglaries involving household servants.
  - 1866 January 17. John B. Gough ALS to Dr. E. S. Crosier; Cin[cinna]ti, [Ohio], 1 page; Unable to fulfill Crosier's request because of a busy schedule "It is always my desire to keep the Temperance Cause whenever it is in my power to do so." Notes his current lecture obligations
  - 1866 February 20. R.K. Cummins ALS to "sister"; Mobile, [Alabama], 7 pages; Discusses work and wages as a shipping clerk for the Mobile and Ohio Railroad Company. Describes travel from Ohio to Louisiana, and the room and board in New Orleans. Suffering from rheumatism. Notes the recovering business climate, cotton industry. Population of southern cities increasing as northerners move south for the cotton industry, but laborers scarce as "so many of the negroes that have died, & have flocked to the cities & town's." Small pox proving deadly among African Americans. Former slaves are "doing better than was expected," and none of the expected disturbances occurred during Christmas and New Year's. Discusses the political climate. "If congress would only admit the southern members, & do away with the Freedmans Bureau, we would be one United Government again, the most dissatisfaction in the south is on account of our still haveing military rule, & the non admittance of their representatives." Mentions Reconstruction policy, Sherman for the Senate, abolition, etc. "I have no doubt now but that the Abolition of Slavery will be the better for the Whites of this country, but in time the extinction of the Blacks." On official "Office of the Mobile and Ohio R.R. Co." stationery.
  - 1866 June 5. R[obert] E. Lee ALS to J. W. Sapsley; Lexington, [Virginia], 3 pages; Informs the father of a student that his son is not keeping up with his studies and should be withdrawn from the college, likely Washington College. "I do not think it would be to his advantage to continue here, without reaping an adequate return for the expenditure of his time & money."
  - 1866 July 20. J[ohn] B[lair] S[mith] Todd ALS to "J. W. Batchedor" [John B. Batchelder]; Fort Randolph, Dakota Ter[ritor]y, 2 pages; Written by Mary Todd Lincoln's cousin and delegate from the Dakota Territory to the House of Representatives. Concerning his photograph "transmitted through the War Dept." "I regret very much that we have no artist in this quarter to touch it up, as you desire-- we are too far removed from the centre of civilization to afford the luxury of the fine arts." Explains his hair color and complexion. "I am glad to hear that you are progressing finely with your picture of the last hours of the President... The subject is a grand one, the tragic death of our Martyr President and well calculated to excited the loftiest emotions of genius." NOTE: John B. Batchelder designed Alonzo Chappel's 1868 painting The Last Hours of Abraham Lincoln.
  - 1866 October 28. Horace Greeley ALS to C. B. [ ]; New York [City, New York], 1 page; Intends to lecture in Cincinnati during the coming winter and will likely be able to provide a lecture for the recipient at that time. "I am so deeply engrossed in our political canvass that I cannot clearly see my way after the election." On Office of the Tribune stationery. [Original in the Horace Greeley Collection]
  - 1866 November 15. Robert Barry Coffin ALS to E. C. Stedman; New York, [New York], 1 page; Poet, also known as Barry Grey, declines invitation to a farewell dinner for James Lorimer Graham (1831-1876).
  - 1867 December 27. [Pop?] ALS to "Brothers"; Bethany, W[est] Virginia, 2 pages; Delayed in writing due to a recent move, possibly from Dowagiac, Michigan. Sharing their new house with another family, "we were acquainted with them in Mich[igan]." Provides great detail about a dinner, possibly for Christmas. Notes the Christmas and New Year vacation for Bethany College, and John will commence after classes resume. [Currently housed in folder with John Lindsey ALS to Jane Lindsey, November 25, 1847]
  - 1868 January 11. Horace Greeley ALS to H. R. Waite; New York [City, New York], 1 page; Agrees to give a lecture on February 3, "my 57th birth-day." Suggests the following topics for the talk: "Great Men, Abraham Lincoln, Self-Made Men, or America Westward of the Mississippi." On "Office of the Tribune" stationery. [Original in the Horace Greeley Collection]
  - 1868 November 7. R[ichard] H[enry] Dana, Jr. ALS to W[illiam] M. Evarts; Boston, [Massachusetts], 8 pages; His supporters deserted or became neutral, resulting in a small vote for Dawes. Massachusetts Congress and the State Central Committee responsible for Butler's success. Comments on Radical Republicans. "But, I do not think B.'s heresies nor his bad character hurt him much."
  - 1868 November 12. David Davis ALS; Bloomington, Ill[inois], 1 page; Regarding Abraham Lincoln's papers. "I have given away all the letters in my possession of Mr. Lincoln's, which it is proper I should give away." The papers left by Lincoln at his death have not yet been examined. "They are in my custody." Will send any that ought to belong to the letter's recipient.
  - 1868 December 30. Johann Strauss Partially printed DS to Josef Homole; Wien, [Austria], 4 pages; Employment contract for musician Josef Homole, written in German. Signed by Johann Strauss as Hofballmusik-Direktor and Capellmeister. Signed by Josef Homole. With wax seal.
  - 1869 February 16. William Tod Otto and Elisha Grote Partially printed DS to James Serrill; Washington, [D. C.], 3 pages [total]; Patent for toy savings bank with illustration of Columbia with scenes of industry and innovation. Includes two illustrations of the "magic Savings Bank" and its schematics, as well as the printed patent. [Located in Oversize Manuscripts]
  - 1869 March 11. Hamilton Fish ALS to [Ulysses S.] Grant; New York, [New York], 3 pages; Declining nomination for Secretary of State. "Nothing would give me greater pleasure than to be associated with your Administration, and to give the best of my humble abilities to aid in advancing the high objects which are the aim of your thoughts & your hopes & to which the Country looks hopefully and confidently for the inauguration of a new era in the Government-- An era of honesty, economy, & fidelity."
  - 1869 April 1. Neal Dow ALS to W[illia]m P[itt] Fessenden; Portland, [Maine], 7 pages; Appreciation for nomination to the diplomatic service. Prefers a position in Switzerland, Belgium, or Holland. Dispute over the Alabama threatens relations with Britain. Likely in reference to British-built warships used by the Confederate States in the Civil War. Gives advice on how to best handle English anxieties and assure American desires are met. "The London Times said the Americans did not care so much for the pecuniary consideration involved in the Alabama claims, as they did for the national humiliation they had suffered-- or fancied they had suffered from the action of the British Gov't and I want them to suffer the humiliation of asking us to be kind enough to send in our bill- and be friends once more." Comments on other English newspaper articles on the affair.
  - 1869 July 23. Susan B. Anthony ALS to Cha[rle]s F. Hatch; New York, [New York], 2 pages; Please to permit Thomas Phelan, who has "faithfully served The Revolution," passage on Hatch's road. "The Erie R.R. Co. have passed him over their road - & I hope the Southern Michigan & Lakeshore will do the same - & thus help one more young man out of this over crowded City to the great west." Written on The Revolution (Woman's Bureau) stationery.
  - 1869 August. Printed Doc.; Milledgeville, [Georgia], 4 pages; "Let every Southern Educator read this. From the Milledgeville Union, August, 1869. Worcester's Quarto Dictionary." Printed flier comparing Webster's dictionary unfavorably to Worcester's dictionary. Comments on dictionaries mislabeling themselves as "Webster's." Notes the history of Worcester's Quarto, Octavo, and Great Pictorial dictionaries. The Webster's dictionary of 1864 displayed various political prejudices and revised definitions of words, including "Congress," "Compact," and "Constitution." Compares the former and new definitions of the word "State," showing the introduction of words and "radical" expressions related to a "National Government." "The doctrines necessarily implied in the new miscalled 'Webster's' definitions, are on ground more than half way from that of the old Republic to an Imperial Despotism, which many are now openly advocating." "We are not - we never were - a 'nation.' We are a community of nations, bound together by the compact of the United States Constitution."
  - [1860s]. [Professor Zendavesta] AM to Emma Dyer, 4 pages; Horoscope of Emma Dyer, with predictions for her life. Written on illustrated letterhead with a printed astrological diagram. "The Stars influence, but do not compel."
  - [1870 July 18]. Elizabeth Cady Stanton ALS to Cha[rle]s Mumford; [New York, New York], 4 pages; Letter regarding preparations and fees for public speeches.
  - 1870 October 6. J[osiah] G[ilbert] Holland ALS to [Daniel?] W. Burton; Springfield, Massachusetts, 1 page; Written in the first year of the publication of Scribner's Monthly. Holland was editor and 1/3 owner of the publication. "My new magazine is soon to appear and I am too much absorbed in the matter to undertake any outside work. When I am running with a heavy train at full speed, I find it very hard to switch off upon another track without harm to the machinery." Hopes he has a good centennial and is grateful for the invitation.
  - 1871 October 14. Ferdinand von Miller ALS to Editor of the Chronicle Times; Burnel House, [Cincinnati, Ohio?], 1 page; Letter written by Miller with the intent of being published in the Chronicle Times. It is a public letter written "To the Citizens of Cincinnati" commending and thanking all who took part in the completion of the Tyler Davidson Fountain. Hopes it will link Cincinnati to Munich. [NOTE: Miller was the second director of the Royal Bronze Foundry in Munich.]
  - 1872 March 4. S[abine] Baring-Gould ALS; Colchester, [England], 1 page; Has sent an article "on the 'Waldeuses,' a demolition of the fables current relatives to them." He is currently at work on "Lives of the Saints," but will try to write a paper on "The Monks and Nature" for him. Is well-read in the history of the Reformation and could possibly write on a related subject. Written on East Mersea Rectory letterhead.
  - 1872 September 16. Peter Cooper ALS to Arthur F. Sptson; New York, [New York], 1 page; "...men in all, the ages that have past, have failed, to Realize the fact -- That hea[l]th, pace, and Competance -- Forms the grand sum of the reall hapyness of mankind -- We fail to realize that that 'Health consists with temperance alone -- And Peace, O vertue Peace is all thine own.' "
  - 1872 November 12. Edward Higginson ALS to [Mrs. Higginson]; Cambridge, [Massachusetts], 5 pages; Eyewitness account of great Boston fire by Harvard student. Notes destruction caused by fire and residents' attempts to save their household goods. Mentions the use of demolition to prevent the further spread of the fire. "The streets were now jam[m]ed with people, firemen from all parts of New England, policemen from New York and thieves from everywhere." An attempted arsonist was shot dead. Served as a guard.
  - 1872 November 25. Joseph R. Hawley ALS to [Ulysses S.] Grant; Hartford, [Connecticut], 2 pages; Letter regarding a preliminary report [not present] from the Centennial Commission. Hawley gives his view on the matter of Government appropriations for the Centennial Exhibition, and advice on what should be included in the Inaugural Address. Hopes for some comment on "specie payment." Congratulates Grant on his recent reelection. "So infamous and persistent were the slanders that it became, in my view, necessary to the national honor that you should be reelected. And I have full confidence that we are to have four years of administration that will rank with the very highest the country has enjoyed." Includes a small printed portrait of Hawley.
  - 1873 January 18. W[illia]m C[arey] Richards ALS to Dappleton & Co.; New York, [New York], 1 page; To the Chairman of the Lecture Committee, YMCA. Looking to fill vacancies in his lecture schedule. The letter is written on a 2-page printed advertising circular, showing Professor W.C. Richards' scientific lecture schedule and topics, 1872-1873. Circular dated May 1, 1872. Includes an addition from August 29, 1872, noting Richards' recent return from Europe, "bringing with him the finest Electrical and Spectroscopic instruments ever constructed."
  - 1873 January 29. Josiah Quincy ALS to Luke Bemis; Boston, [Massachusetts], 2 pages; Sending a memoir of Gridley Bryant, "the Engineer of the Quincy railroad which was the first in the United States." Remarks on the public interest (and benefit) surrounding the founding of the Quincy Railroad. Comments on its relationship to granite.
  - 1873 March 29. Edwin L. Stanton ALS to W[illiam] P. Dole; Washington, D.C., 1 page; Enclosing a bill [not present].
  - [18]73 April 22. Henry Ward Beecher ALS to [George W. Bungay]; s.l., 2 pages; Declines a request for him to speak. "...tho' I preach on temperance, I have no lectures—and off handed talks I cannot give—with any comfort,-- except at home."
  - 1874 Janurary 31. R[ichard] H[enry] Dana, Jr. ALS to [William M.] Evarts; [Boston, Massachusetts], 4 pages; Discusses Evarts' consideration of a judicial appointment. "I have always doubted whether the post would have suited you. Your talents and temperament fit you best for forensic life... You shine most in debate." Thoughts on the position of Chief Justice, Congress, and the distinction between men of merit and those who receive rewards. Mentions President Grant.
  - 1874 April 18. Th[omas] Nast Illustration Signed; s.l., 1 page; Pen-and-ink self-portrait of Thomas Nast lecturing to a displeased crowd.